2017年8月21日，全世界都被美国日全食刷屏了
On August 21st 2017 what is being dubbed as the great American Eclipse would take
从西海岸俄勒冈到延绵4313公里直到
place on a path 2680 miles long that goes from Oregon on the west coast
东海岸的南卡罗来纳州，99年以来，日全食又一次横跨了美国
to South Carolina on the east and will be the first total eclipse in the u.s.
从东海岸到西海岸。全食区阴影宽度
to go coast-to-coast in 99 years. The width of the shadow
——也就是月球完全挡住太阳的区域
where the Sun will be completely blocked by the moon is
——宽113公里，阴影移动速度每小时2400公里
70 miles wide and will travel across the land at over 1500 miles an hour 2,400
而从地面上看，全食的时间从
kilometers an hour. For those on the ground the time of totality will vary from just
俄勒冈州不到两分钟，肖尼市最长2分44秒
under two minutes in Oregon to a maximum of two minutes 44 seconds in the Shawnee
到伊利诺伊州南部的国家森林公园部分地区时长可
National Forest in Southern Illinois but for a few the eclipse will last for over
超过7分钟。而在天上，两名田纳西州的科学家
seven minutes. High above Tennessee two scientists will
通过追逐影子，延长了连续观测日全食的时间
extend the time of continuous observation by chasing the shadow of the
他们乘坐改装过的WB-57飞机，装有高分辨率
moon in a pair of modified WB 57 bombers. Armed with high resolution and
高速相机。来自美国西南研究院的一组团队在NASA的资助下
high-speed cameras a team from a Southwest Research Institute funded by
将首次拍摄纳耀斑的图片——在太阳外层边缘
NASA will aim to capture the first ever images of nanoflares small explosions of
频繁发生的小型能量爆发。因为他们飞行高度
energy that frequently take place in the sun's outer layers. Because they fly at
在五万英尺，15公里左右
an altitude of 50,000 feet or 15 kilometres of just over nine miles the
从WB-57飞机上看到的天空会比地面20到30倍
view from the WB-57 s will be 20 to 30 times darker than that on the ground and
因为几乎没有大气的干扰。两名科学家和飞行员向东飞行时
almost free atmospheric disturbance. For the two scientists and their pilots the
可以看到超过7分钟的日全食
Eclipse will appear to last for over seven minutes as they fly eastwards. Each
每次日食在地球上留下的影子都不同，这取决于月球
solar eclipse follows a different course over the earth dictated by the moon's
与地球、太阳的相对位置。同时也导致
position and the Earth's orbit around the Sun. This in turn influences the speed of
阴影区移动速度与地球上的日食时长，这使得地球上所有地方
the moon's shadow across the earth and the length of time that each eclipse can
都有看到日食的可能。一万两千年内——从公元前四千年
be viewed at any point on the ground. The longest Eclipse for 12,000 years, 4000 BC
到公元后八千年，最长的日食将发生在2186年7月4日
to at least 8000 AD will be on July 4 2186
持续7分32秒，从东太平洋
and it will last for seven minutes and 32 seconds and start over the eastern
到南美洲北部再横跨整个大西洋
Pacific moved over northern part of South America and over the Atlantic
然而，44年前，1973年6月30日
Ocean. However a little over 44 years ago on June the 30th 1973 the longest total
人们预测到了千年一遇的日全食
solar eclipse in a thousand years was predicted to occur with a maximum of
最长持续时间7分4秒，横穿整个撒哈拉沙漠
seven minutes and four seconds of totality over Saharan Africa. This
这次特殊的天象遇到了另一个特殊的事件
extraordinary astronomic event coincided with another fortunate circumstance the
世界上第一款超音速客机——协和式客机的研发工作
world's first supersonic airliner Concorde was nearing the end of its
非常顺利并接近尾声。1972年英法两国科学家
successful test program. In 1972 British and French scientists recognized a
得到了这次千载难逢的机会，他们可以乘坐超音速飞机
special opportunity for this Eclipse the path of totality would travel at speeds
以两马赫的速度追逐月球的影子
which could be matched by Concorde just above Mach 2. By flying one of the
协和客机原型机之一向南飞行进入月球阴影，上面的科学家们
prototype airliners South to join the part of the moon shadow, scientists
可以观察超过70分钟的日全食，是从地面最长
would be able to observe the Eclipse from over 70 minutes, 10 times longer
观测时间的十倍。法国天文学家Pierre Léna首先
than the longest on the ground. Pierre Léna a French astronomer pitched the
向协和式客机飞行员提出了这个想法，飞行员之后又向
idea to one of a Concorde test pilots who then suggested the possibility to
他的老板说了这事，老板听了感觉一颗赛艇
his bosses at aérospatiale, the French state-owned operator of the
认为这是个非常好的，向世人展示
prototype jet. The opportunity was warmly received as it was an opportunity to
他们最新款超音速客机的机会。然而这次任务还需要面对一些
show off the unique capabilities of the new aircraft. The mission posed some
技术上的挑战，因为日食发生的位置几乎在飞机
technical challenges however, because the eclipse would appear almost directly
的正上方，所以飞机的天花板上装了特制的石英舷窗
overhead, specialized quartz portholes had to be installed in the roof of the
可以承受超音速飞行的压强与高温
plane able to withstand the extreme pressure and heat of supersonic flight.
另外，所有科学设备都要定制、检查
In addition all scientific instruments had to be checked and modified to remove
减少一切短路的危险，防止加压客舱内发生火灾
any risk of short-circuit that might cause a fire in the pressurized cabin. In
1973年2月，任务正式批准，五个团队分别来自
February 1973 the flight was given the official go-ahead and five teams of
英法美三国的科学家们登上了协和式客机
scientists were chosen from Britain France and America to fill Concorde cabin
上面有各种观察仪器。1973年6月30日早
with a variety of observational experiments. On the morning of June 30th
飞机从大加那利岛起飞
1973 the supersonic airliner took off from Gran Canaria and turned to
切入毛里塔尼亚上空的阴影区。之后一直跟着
intercept the racing shadow of a moon over Mauritania. There they followed it
阴影横穿撒哈拉，直到飞机最后不得不在为数不多的机场中
across the Sahara until they had to land at one of the few airports which had the
的乍得降落。任务圆满成功
stopping distance that Concorde required in Chad. The mission was a success
协和001航班总共观察到74分钟、有史以来在地球上持续时间最长
Concorde 001 observed 74 minutes of totality, the longest ever observation of
的日全食。这个记录一直保持到今天而且很难
a solar eclipse from Earth. This record still stands today and is unlikely to be
再被打破，因为如今已经没有飞机
broken anytime soon if ever this is because currently there are no aircraft
能飞这么快、这么远。即使有一些军机
that can fly fast enough for long enough. Even though there are military jets that
可以飞这么快，但它们超音速下航程没有协和那么长
can fly faster they don't have the long-distance endurance of Concorde at
飞机内也没有那么大空间放科学设备。1999年三架协和客机
supersonic speed and they don't have the room for the equipment. In 1999 three Concordes,
——一架来自法国、一架来自英国——载着乘客而不是科学家
one French and two British flew filled with tourists instead of scientists and
在欧洲的一次日全食发生时追逐影子一段时间
chased the moons shadow for a short period of time during an eclipse over
但之后的“日全食之旅”在2000年7月发生的
Europe. However further Concorde Eclipse tours were canceled after the crash of
协和4590航班坠毁事故之后就都取消了
Concorde flight 4590 from Paris in July 2000. The original
之前那架改装过的协和客机还可以在法国巴黎北部
modified Concorde can still be seen in its special livery of the Air and Space
勒布尔歇航空航天博物馆里看到。如今太阳的研究
Museum the Le Bourget , north of Paris in France. Today solar research is done
主要是由像SOHO（太阳和日球层探测器）这样的探测器完成的
mostly by dedicated space satellites like Soho for Solar and Heliospheric
它能使用LASCO（大角度分光日冕观测仪）
Observatory which creates its own artificial Eclipse with the LASCO or large
“创造出”日食，这使得像1973年协和客机那样在地球上观测
Angle and Spectrometric Cronograph Instrument making airborne observations
日食显得没有那么有意义了
much less significant than in the days of Concorde flight of 1973 but it's
但作为某种纪念，如前文所说，NASA还是会在日食时派出两架WB-57进行观测
legacy will live on in the flight of NASA's twin WB 57 s later this month.